Okay, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody.
Today's דף Daf is מ"ב, Mem Beis, and we pick up on
the bottom of מ"א עמוד ב', Mem Aleph Amud Beis,
תשמע. Tashma. And we are dealing with the issue about the debate
of רבי Rebbe and the רבנן, Rabbanan, whether you can half-free a
slave. And the גמרא Gemara wanted to have two approaches to this.
רבה Rabbah said it was a debate about a שטר shtar but
with כסף, kessef, which is fundamentally about the property aspect of a
slave, everybody agreed that you could half-free him, that he could half-free
himself. But שטר, shtar, which was about the personal status, that was
the debate where רבי Rebbe said it worked and the חכמים Chachamim
said it did not work. And then you had עולא Ulla that
said the opposite, well that said that no, by שטר shtar of
course it doesn't work and the debate is by כסף. kessef. And
the גמרא Gemara demonstrated with a ברייתא Beraysa that clearly they're debating
about a שטר, shtar, that רבי Rebbe does say that actually a
שטר shtar can work halfway. And it's an open question whether everybody
would agree that כסף kessef works halfway or that's a debate as
well. So now we continue with the גמרא, Gemara, תשמע, Tashma, about
20 lines from the bottom on מ"א עמוד ב'. Mem Aleph Amud
Beis. תשמע: Tashma: והפדה לא נפדתה, vehispaday lo nifsasah, this is the
פרשה parsha by the שפחה כנענית, Shifcha Canaanis, by a case about
a man who sleeps with a non-Jewish slave who was somewhat
designated to another man, to another slave, or a Hebrew slave, and
he's חייב chayav in a קרבן. korban. And the question is, what
was the status of this non-Jewish slave? So the פסוק pasuk says,
והפדה לא נפדתה או חופשה לא ניתן לה, vehispaday lo nifsasah o
chuphshah lo nittan lah, she has not been redeemed and her freedom
has not been given to her. So the question is, is she
a complete slave? Or is והפדה לא נפדתה, vehispaday lo nifsasah, although
it's the Torah's way of emphasis like נקה לא ינקה, nakei lo
yenakeh, she surely not be cleansed, והפדה לא נפדתה vehispaday lo nifsasah
as surely not been redeemed? But the way the גמרא Gemara is
choosing to read it is that it's a halfway, like some might
read נקה לא ינקה, nakei lo yenakeh, some people are cleansed and
some are not, here והפדה, vehispaday, she's redeemed and לא נפדתה, lo
nifsasah, she's not redeemed, she's partially redeemed. And then that would be
a source for the idea that there could be a slave could
be half redeemed, at least by money. So let's take a look.
והפדה, vehispaday, יכל לכל, yachol lakol, maybe she's completely redeemed? תלמוד לומר
Talmud lomar לא נפדתה, lo nifsasah, she isn't redeemed. If לא נפדתה,
lo nifsasah, she isn't redeemed, יכל לכל, yachol lakol, maybe fully not
redeemed? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar והפדה, vehispaday, she is redeemed. הכיצד? Ha
keitzad? And what is this story? What's the case? פדויה ואינה פדויה,
Piduyah ve'eina piduyah, she is half redeemed, בכסף ובשווי כסף, bekessef uveshvei
kessef, and that came through, redemption comes through money. So here you
have the idea that at least the process of redeeming can work
halfway, so that's all about the property ownership. אין לי אלא בכסף,
Ein li ela bekessef, I know that somebody can only be redeemed
by money, שטר מנין, shtar minayin, how do I know that somebody
can be redeemed by a writ, by a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur,
or somebody can be freed, excuse me, תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar והפדה
לא
נפדתה או חופשה לא ניתן לה, vehispaday lo nifsasah o chuphshah lo
nittan lah, and her freedom has not been given to her.
ולהלן אומר Ulehallan omer וכתב לה ספר כריתות, vechasav lah sepher kerisus,
writes for her a writ of divorce, and the לה לה, lah
lah, the classic לה לה lah lah comparison tells you that first
of all, it's one basis we learn that slaves have the obligation
equal to that of women, including the bar slave. But here we
learn from the לה לה lah lah that it means that the
same way a woman is divorced with a writ, a slave is
freed with a writ. So, מה להלן בשטר אף כאן בשטר. ma
lehallan beshtar aph kan beshtar. So then we have the idea that
a slave is freed both with money and with a writ. And
the case of money, we have an idea that it was done
even half of a freedom can be achieved, it's not a be
all or nothing affair. So the גמרא Gemara says, אין לי אלא,
ein li ela, אף כאן בשטר. aph kan beshtar. אין לי אלא
ein li ela חציה בכסף או כולה בשטר, chetzyah bekessef o kullah
beshtar, all I know from the פסוק pasuk is that it's possible
to do halfway by money, or if you're going to use a
שטר, shtar, that would be presumably the entire slave, like an entire
woman by divorce. חציה בשטר מנין? chetzyah beshtar minayin? How do I
know that it's possible to even free half of a slave with
a שטר, shtar, to do a half freedom, not the whole thing?
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar והפדה לא נפדתה או חופשה לא ניתן לה,
vehispaday lo nifsasah o chuphshah lo nittan lah, two parts are connected.
מקיש שטר לכסף, Makish shtar lekessef, it links the שטר shtar to
the money. מה כסף בין כולה בין חציה, Mah kessef bein kullah
bein chetzyah, the same way money, it's all but it could also
be partially, והפדה לא נפדתה, vehispaday lo nifsasah, you could do a
half redemption. אף שטר נמי בין כולה בין חציה, Aph shtar nami
bein kullah bein chetzyah, the same is true by a שטר. shtar.
Okay, so this is a very nice ברייתא Beraysa that says that
we from והפדה לא נפדתה vehispaday lo nifsasah we learned that a
slave could be redeemed halfway, and from the connection to the שטר,
shtar, we learn the שטר shtar could work halfway. Completely consistent with
רבי's Rebbe position. So the גמרא Gemara says, הא בשלמא Ha bishlamah
לרב יוסף, le-Rav Yosef, according to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, בתר דאיתותב,
basar de'isosseh,
after he was challenged partially and he had to concede that there
is a debate by שטר, shtar, then he would argue that the
debate is both by שטר shtar and by כסף. kessef. So fine,
this all works like רבי. Rebbe. הא מני? Ha man? רבי! Rebbe!
This is רבי, Rebbe, that says that it works by שטר shtar
and it works by כסף. kessef. And the חכמים Chachamim would disagree
with both parts of this ברייתא. Beraysa. אלא לרבה, Ella le-Rabbah,
but according to רבה, Rabbah, רישא דברי הכל, reisha divrei hakol, the
beginning that says that it works by כסף, kessef, that's everybody. Even
the חכמים Chachamim say that you can do a half redemption by
כסף. kessef. הסיפא רבי? Ha-seifa Rebbi? So how could it be that
the beginning where it says it works halfway by כסף, kessef, that's
everybody, yet where it says that it works halfway by שטר, shtar,
that's only רבי? Rebbi? How could such a thing be, which is
such a bizarre question? Because why not? Why doesn't רבי Rebbi start
with the position that is agreed upon and then he uses it
to examine his next position which is debated, which is that they
also say, which is that he says that even a שטר shtar
can work halfway. So that's basically what the גמרא Gemara says, but
it's even strange that the question is even being asked. So אמר
לך רבא, Amar lach Rava, אין, in, yes, רישא דברי הכל, reisha
divrei hakol, the first part where it says that it works halfway
by כסף, kessef, it can work halfway, that everybody agrees on, סיפא
רבי, seifa Rebbi, and then the second part where he says and
even a שטר shtar can work halfway, that's רבי, Rebbi, that's exactly
the area of debate. Okay. רב אשי אמר רבי היא, Rav Ashi
amar Rebbi hi, as a whole thing is רבי, Rebbi, אלא, ela,
רבי, Rebbi, רבי, Rebbi, which basically is a similar answer, but
רב אשי Rav Ashi just says, רבי אמר כולה ואיכא דתרוייהו קנה.
Rebbi amar kulla ve-iska d'tarveihu kana. Right, רבי, Rebbi, you don't have
to say that the first half of the ברייתא braita is a,
the author of it is דברי הכל. divrei hakol. The whole ברייתא
braita is רבי. Rebbi. רבי Rebbi is basically saying, I say it
works halfway by כסף, kessef, something we all agree upon, and then
רבי Rebbi goes to the end of the ברייתא braita and says,
and once we all agree that halfway works by כסף, kessef, I'm
going to say halfway works even בשטר. bish'tar. So the author is
all רבי, Rebbi, even though the first half is, is everybody conceded
on. Why not start with a point that everybody can agree to?
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא
מתניתין דקתני מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין, ela matnitin d'katni mi
she-chetzyo eved ve-chetzyo ben chorin, now we have our משנה. Mishna. Our
משנה Mishna says, our משנה Mishna is dealing with somebody that's half
slave and half free, and whether we force the master to free
him in order that he can get married to a woman and
have children. So that משנה, Mishna, בשלמא לרבא מוקים לה בכסף דברי
הכל. bishlama l'Rava mukim lah be-kessef divrei hakol. Who's the author of
that משנה? Mishna? So according to רבא, Rava, no problem. It would
be that he was half redeemed with money, and everybody could agree
that such a phenomenon could occur at half-free, half-slave, if he was
half redeemed by money. אלא רב יוסף, Ela Rav Yosef, according to
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef says according to the
רבנן Rabbanan you cannot, the רבנן Rabbanan would say not only can
you not half-free a slave with a שטר, shtar, you can't half-free
a slave with money. So according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, according to
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, where do you get this phenomenon of somebody
that's a half-slave? It doesn't work by כסף kessef and it certainly
doesn't work by שטר. shtar. So
אלא רב יוסף לימא רבי היא ולא רבנן? Ela Rav Yosef leima
Rebbi hi velo Rabbanan? Let's say it's רבי Rebbi and not the
רבנן. Rabbanan. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, רבינא Ravina will tell you, no,
בעבד ששני שותפים ודברי הכל, be-eved she-shnei shutfin ve-divrei hakol, which we
sort of already knew because of רש"י Rashi on the משנה Mishna
earlier. We're dealing with a case that it's owned by two masters,
and everybody agrees, because in that case one master can write a
writ, or presumably can have the slave redeemed, and he totally frees
himself, and he totally, sort of, frees his own ownership. And therefore
that works, even though the whole status hasn't changed. One way of
thinking about this is he did an act which although it would
change the whole status, but it's being held back by somebody else's
ownership of him. So therefore it's not seen as a fundamental lack
of that ability of of that act to change, to change the
slave. This by the way also assumes that רבי, Rebbi, right, this
is assuming that רבי Rebbi and the רבנן Rabbanan argue both by
a writ and by כסף. kessef. So therefore if you were just,
if you were to own the whole slave and try to redeem
him partway or free him partway, that would not work. You have
to do something that defines his whole status, that transforms his whole
status. But here, if it's just the part that you own, you're
doing
fully, דברי הכל. divrei hakol. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so now
רבא Rava says, מחלוקת בששחרר חציו והניח חציו. machlokes be-she-shichrer chetzyo ve-hiniach
chetzyo. The debate of רבי Rebbi and the רבנן Rabbanan is when
you freed half and you retained half. אבל שחרר חציו ומכר חציו
או נתן במתנה חציו כיון דנפיק מיניה כולה דברי הכל קנה.
Aval shichrer chetzyo u-machar chetzyo o nasan be-matanah chetzyo
keivan d'nafik minei kulla divrei hakol kana. So this is sort of
like a variation of the idea that when he was still partially
owned by somebody else. Let's say it starts that it wasn't owned
half by somebody else, but in
one, now if you went ahead and you sold half to somebody
and then freed half, then of course that would work. That would
be like just recreating the situation that first half maybe it wasn't
owned by somebody else, which is okay, that's a sale, you can
do that, you're not changing status. And now that you're coming to
free the half that you own, that's what was established before that
everybody agrees that that can work on the half that you own,
and you can get somebody who is a half-slave and a half-free
person. But let's say you actually were trying to do both of
them at the same time. So if you're trying to do both
of them at the same time in one act, you, in one
act, in one act you
give
somebody to take possession of two שטרות. shtarot. One שטר shtar that
transfers possession to ראובן Reuven for half the slave, and one שטר
shtar that
frees. So we are saying that the same way it works with
that since two שטרות, shtaros, since an act of שחרור shichror is
not considered to be not a full act if you're doing every
part of the slave that you own, if you're completely divesting yourself
of your slave, so here too that's true even if it's all
simultaneous. In this one moment you're fully divesting yourself of your slave,
when you're done with your שחרור, shichror, you're not retaining any part,
and therefore that can work. We also explain this based on the
comparison to the get isha. Rashi says דבהא דנפיק כולה מנפקא מן
אשה de-be-ha de-nafik kullah minafkah min isha that
the problem is not the status of halfly half slave as we
know, where the case is when you free him and he's already
half owned. The problem is the act of doing a partial freedom
and Rashi says the emphasis there is not that it has to
result in him being freed, off of something we know when he's
already owned halfway by somebody else.
The problem is that your act has to be a total divesting
of yourself from your slave, a total sense that he is no
longer my slave at all. If something else, somebody else's slave partly,
that's nothing that I can control. So even if you do that
at the same time, transfer half ownership and free your half, that
actually also works. Okay, so let's read that again. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, מחלוקת בששחרר חציו והניח חציו machlokes be-she-shichrer chetzyo ve-hiniach chetzyo that
you retained to continue to retain a half and did not totally
free and and divorce yourself from that slave. אבל שחרר חציו ומכר
חציו aval shichrer chetzyo u-machar chetzyo but if you freed half and
sold half, או נתן במתנה o nasan be-matanah or gave the other
half in a gift and you did this all at the same
time, או נתן במתנה חציו, o nasan be-matanah chetzyo, excuse me, כיון
דנפיק מיניה כוליה keivan de-nafik minei kulei since you are completely taking
your slave away from yourself, right, so divesting yourself of the slave,
not retaining any part of it, דברי הכל קנה divrei ha-kol kanah
everybody would say that that would work. Okay, אמר ליה אביי, Amar
lei Abaye,
now we're going to see if this is really true. If even
the Rabbanan who argue on Rabbi and who would presumably agree in
the case when already part of the slave is owned by somebody
else, would they agree that this would be true if it were
at the same time
selling half and freeing half? So let's take a look. אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so Abaye said to him, ובכולי לא פליגי,
u-ve-kulei lo peligi, are you telling me that they would not disagree
in a case when it was fully divesting yourself of the slave
if you were doing a half-half type of a thing? והתניא חדה,
ve-ha-tanya chada, but we taught in a Baraita, הכותב נכסיו לשני עבדיו,
ha-kosev nechasav li-shnei avadav, you write over all your estate to two
of your servants, slaves, excuse me.
So what's the story? So now they each own half the estate
and they each own half of each other because they are part
of the estate. So therefore and presumably because in that act since
you're giving each slave half, so each slave you're giving half of
himself and half of the other slave. So because presumably you're giving
him half of himself, he's half free and that allows him to
own property. That allows the sale to have gone through. But now
he's not fully free because half of him is owned by the
other slave. So what do they do? הם משחררים זה את זה,
hem meshachrerim zeh es zeh, they write a writ of freedom to
one another. They free one another. Now normally a slave can't own
property let alone another slave, although I think as I've mentioned before
that in ancient Rome slaves did own slaves. But anyway because he's
half free, he is actually able to own property and own the
other slave, the half of him that's free, and that therefore he's
able to free that other half slave. And therefore they free one
another. Presumably this would assume that if you
that in the act of selling the slave to himself even if
there's a question of מפקיר עבד תחת גט שחרור, mafkir eved tachas
get shichror, presumably selling the slave to himself or giving the slave
to himself as an act of a gift and the slave takes
possession, that actually unquestionably constitutes a שחרור. shichror. Maybe it's also with
a שטר, shtar, it's a שטר מתנה shtar matanah that's part of
what makes it work, but that's interesting that here the status issue
has changed automatically with the monetary one. Anyway, so the Gemara says
like this: So that works. Okay. Now that was, notice, that each
slave was only half free at that moment. You totally divested yourself
of the slaves, but the but each individual slave, what, you freed
half of him and you gave half of him to the other
slave. And that works. And Rava has been saying that according to
the Rabbanan that would work according to everybody, even according to the
Rabbanan. תא שמע, Ta shema, let's look at the next Baraita. והתניא
אידך, Ve-ha-tanya idach, but we taught in another
Baraita, האומר כל נכסי נתונים לפלוני ופלוני עבדי, ha-omer kol nechasai nesunim
li-peloni u-feloni avadai, somebody says all of my property is given to
Reuven and Shimon my slaves, אף עצמן לא קנו, af atzman lo
kanu, it doesn't work. Now that sounded exactly like the other thing.
You wrote over all your property to both of your slaves. You
said that all of my property is given over to both of
my slaves. It doesn't work at all. Why not? It sounds like
that in that act they remain slaves because they remain slaves they
could not take possession. of any of the property. Well, why is
it different? So the גמרא Gemara says, אף על פי דמאי לאו?
af al pi demai lav? הא רבי הא רבנן? ha Rebbi ha
rabbanan? It must be the difference of רבי Rebbi and רבנן. rabbanan.
The first ברייתא braita was according to רבי, Rebbi, it was a
half freedom of each slave and therefore they were able to take
possession of the property and able to free one another. The second
one would be according to רבנן, rabbanan, you're only half-freeing each slave
so you're doing nothing because you're giving everything to both of them
and therefore they can't take possession of property, they can't take possession
of themselves, they can't take possession of anything, nothing works, okay, of
each other, etc. It was only a half freedom. So you see
that according to the רבנן rabbanan half-freeing your slave doesn't work, even
if it's done by you totally divesting yourself of your full slave.
You've given half to the slave himself and half to the other
slave, you've fully divested yourself and nevertheless it does not work. So
you see the רבנן rabbanan do not agree in that case. So
the גמרא Gemara says, sounds like a nice way of dealing with
those ברייתות, braitot, but no, not necessarily. אידי ואידי רבנן, idi ve'idi
rabbanan, we could say they're both the רבנן. rabbanan. So if they're
both the רבנן rabbanan and the רבנן rabbanan agree when you divest,
fully divest yourself, why does the second case not work? הא דאמר
כולהו הא דאמר חצי חצי. ha de'amar kulhu ha de'amar chatzi chatzi.
It depends if you say to each slave, I'm giving you Reuven
all and I'm giving you Shimon all, that was the first case,
and then when you did it, since they can't both have all,
it works out fifty-fifty and that works because you're fully divesting yourself
and the רבנן rabbanan would agree. And in the second case where
it doesn't work, you say, I'm giving you Reuven half and you
Shimon half. And that doesn't work. Now the question is why doesn't
that work? That should just be I'm selling, I'm freeing half of
you Reuven to yourself, and I'm selling the other half to, well,
let's get whatever, has to have a non-Jewish name, but anyway, I'm
giving half of Frederick to yourself, and I'm selling the other half
to Reuven over there. Okay, so that seems to be that would
be a case that we say the רבנן rabbanan would agree. So
if they would agree when you free half and when you sell
half, why does, why everybody's on camera by the way, why they'd
agree when you give half and sell half, why does it not
work when it's, why does it not work when it's in a
case where you are selling or you are giving half-half to the
two slaves? Even if you don't say all-all, you say half-half, that's
exactly a case that should work. Why does it not work? So
רש"י Rashi says, it's a debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot,
they both give answers that are not fully or are not fully
satisfying you might say. רש"י Rashi says that the case is
that
because you said I'm giving you Frederick half and you Reuven half,
maybe you're in both of them you're referring to the same half
and therefore you're not fully divesting yourself of the slave. תוספות Tosafot
says come on, it doesn't sound like that at all. It sounds
like anything short of saying all-all would not work, even if you
said I'm giving you this half and I'm giving you that half.
We're clearly talking about different halves. So תוספות Tosafot says the reason
it doesn't work is because since it won't work sequentially, it doesn't
work at the same time either. But if I were to say
I'm giving you Frederick half and then you said and then ten
minutes later you said I'm giving the other half to Reuven over
there, that doesn't work because you do not fully divest yourself of
the slave. And therefore, since it doesn't work sequentially, it doesn't work
also at the same time. Whereas if you say I'm giving you
Frederick all of yourself, all the property, and then you said I'm
giving Reuven all the property, that would work. Frederick, at least for
Frederick, he would get all the property and he'd be free. So
therefore when you do all-all at the same time, it also does
work.
So that's the way תוספות Tosafot explains it, that because it would
work sequentially, so because it would work sequentially, that because it doesn't
work sequentially,
it also doesn't work simultaneously. Of course it's not fully satisfying, תוספות
Tosafot has his own questions, but also if you think about it,
the basic case of half-half that we started with that the רבנן
rabbanan agreed to
also doesn't work sequentially. It works in one sequence. It works if
you say I'm giving half to Reuven and then half to Frederick.
It doesn't work in the other sequence, but maybe that's enough. As
long as it can work
in one of the sequential arrangements, it can work simultaneously. But in
this case of the two slaves, right, it won't work in either
of the sequential arrangements. If you try to give a slave half
of the property, nothing happens, he does not get free, okay? And
if you,
so therefore because half-half doesn't work in either the sequential arrangement, it
doesn't work simultaneously. All right, so that's a basic, those are the
basic, so that's a little confusing, but that's basically what we've done.
We've tried to say, so one more time,
we've actually, we've tried to say that according to the argument of
רבא Rava was that the רבנן rabbanan agree when it's simultaneously freeing
half and giving half that it works. We've showed that this seems
to even the רבנן rabbanan would agree this doesn't work. We've shown
that
this does work, we've shown it doesn't sound like that. It sounds
like a case that just doesn't work
where you give all your property to your two slaves and it
doesn't work. Why not? Shouldn't that be like half-half that and where
you're divesting yourself fully? Gemara says well if it's all all it
does work and that each own half and that is the case
of רבא, Rava, you're fully divesting yourself. But you say half-half it
doesn't. Why is that different? So again Tosafot says that's different because
that doesn't work sequentially. If you tried to do that sequentially with
each individual slave, nothing would happen. You would just be trying to
free half a slave which nothing works. But does it work when
you do all all? But therefore if you did it sequentially the
slave that you said all to, at least he would own himself
and he'd be free. Or if you did half-half with a free
person, that also would work sequentially. First you sell the free person
half and then you free the other half for the slave. But
half-half with two slaves does not work. So that's the specific reason,
but otherwise what רבא Rava is saying you're still going to defend
that the רבנן Rabbanan would agree with a case of half-half.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אה מה
דקתני סיפא, Ha mi-d'katni seifa, but what about the end of the
ברייתא braita says, אם אמר חצי חצי לא קנו, Im amar chetzi
chetzi lo kanu, if you said half-half it doesn't work. The end
of that ברייתא braita when you were trying to give all of
it to two slaves it doesn't work and then the ברייתא braita
continues and if you said half-half it doesn't work as well presumably.
So מכלל דרשא דאמר כולה, Mi-chlal d'reisha d'amar kula, that sounds like
the first case where we're saying it doesn't work when you try
to give it all to two slaves is that you said all
of it, not half-half, and even that doesn't work. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, פירושא קמפרש, Perusha ka-mefaraish, it's explaining אף אזמן לא
קנו
כיצד, Af azman lo kanu keitzad, what's the case when you try
to give all your property to two slaves it doesn't work? כגון
דאמר חצי חצי, Ke-gon d'amar chetzi chetzi, when you said half-half, but
if you said all of it then they that would work. הכא
נמי מסתברא, Hacha nami mistabra, that also makes sense. אי סלקא דעתך
רישא דאמר כולה, Ei salka daitach reisha d'amar kula, if you think
the רישא reisha is when you said all and it doesn't work
by all, then saying and half-half doesn't work, השתא דאמר כולה לא
קנו, Hashta d'amar kula lo kanu, if saying explicitly I'm giving it
all to both of you doesn't work, חצי חצי
מיבעיא? Chetzi chetzi mibaya? Obviously what type of question would it be?
Of course half-half wouldn't work. Says no, אם משום הא לא איריא,
Im mishum ha lo irya, if that was your only proof that
wouldn't prove anything. תנא סיפא לגלויי רישא, Tana seifa l'galuye reisha, we're
telling the end in order to make it clear what the beginning
case is, שלא תאמר רישא דאמר חצי חצי, Shelo tomar reisha d'amar
chetzi chetzi, you shouldn't say exactly what you did say, which is
when does it not work when you try to give it to
two slaves? If you said half-half. אבל אמר כולה קנה, Aval amar
kula kana, but if you said all, I'm giving it all to
two slaves maybe you would think it does work. תנא סיפא דאמר
חצי חצי, Tana seifa d'amar chetzi chetzi, so it says in the
end if you said half-half it also doesn't work. So מכלל דרשא
דאמר
כולה, Mi-chlal d'reisha d'amar kula, you should realize the first case where
we're talking about was when you said I'm giving it all to
two slaves and even so it doesn't work, תנא סיפא דאמר כולה
ואפילו הכי לא קנו.
Tana seifa d'amar kula v'afillu
hachi lo kanu. This ברייתא braita we don't know, the end of
it is a case of half-half, the beginning is unclear. We're arguing
that the beginning is also half-half, it's the same case and that's
why in that case if you try to give half-half to a
slave and a free person, רבא Rava says רבנן Rabbanan would agree
to say it would work. But you tried to give half-half to
two slaves, that doesn't work. But he still is going to argue
that the רבנן Rabbanan would say that if you did half to
a slave and half to a free person even the רבנן Rabbanan
would say that that does work.
ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, if you want I can tell you, לא
קשיא. lo kashya. כאן בשטר אחד כאן בשני שטרות, Kan bi-shtar echad
kan bi-shnei shtarot, it's a difference of one document or two documents.
If it was in one, if you gave in two documents to
ראובן Reuven and to excuse me to your two slaves, you get
all, you get all, it does work. But if you tried in
one, and he said half. But if you tried in one document,
I am giving all my property to ראובן ושמעון Reuven v'Shimon my
slaves, that doesn't work. Why not? Even if you said all. Because
as רש"י Rashi says this שטר shtar also has to work as
a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur and a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur by
a גט, get, we learn out that it can't have a גט
get for two women at the same time if you free both
your wives. So also you cannot have a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur
for two slaves at the same time. So therefore it's a technical
reason even if you were that even though you could free half
your slave if you did it in this way, you can't free
two of your slaves with one document. And that's the case that
it does not work. ואיבעית אימא לא קשיא כאן בשטר אחד כאן
בשני שטרות. V'iba'it eima lo kashya kan bi-shtar echad kan bi-shnei shtarot.
בשטר אחד מאי איריא חצי חצי אפילו אמר כולה נמי לא קנו?
Bi-shtar echad mai irya chetzi chetzi afillu amar kula nami lo kanu?
If so, why are we,
why does the end of the ברייתא braita say we're talking about
a case which she now said it's explaining the beginning of the
ברייתא, braita, why are we talking only about a case of חצי
חצי? chetzi chetzi? The idea of one שטר shtar for two slaves
is a fundamental, that's fundamentally doesn't work, it doesn't matter what language
you have in the ברייתא. braita. So why would the ברייתא braita
bother to mention the idea of חצי חצי chetzi chetzi as if
that was
something which was a חידוש chiddush or that was something which would
make possibly have made a difference one way or the other? Once
you're talking about a שטר shtar for two slaves fundamentally the whole
thing is invalid. הכי נמי קאמר, Hachi nami ka-amar,
you're right, this is what it would say. אף אזמן לא קנו,
Af azman lo kanu, when you try to give your entire property
to two slaves they do not, it doesn't work. במה דברים אמורים
בשטר אחד, Bamei devarim amurim bi-shtar echad, that's by one שטר shtar
because fundamentally you can't have one שטר shtar to free two slaves.
אבל בשני Aval bi-shnei and there I obviously different, it doesn't make
a difference whether it's כולו kulo or חציו. chetzyo. אבל בשני שטרות
קנו, aval bishnei shtaros kanu,
but if it's two שטרות, shtaros, that does work, because this is
again רבא's Rava's position, that according to the רבנן rabbanan it does
work if you divest yourself fully, even in two halves. ואימא אמר
חציו חציו, v'eima amar chetzyo chetzyo,
but if he said half-half, even in two שטרות, shtaros, אף בשני
שטרות נמי לא קנו, af bishnei shtaros nami lo kanu, even that
doesn't work, maintaining our position that there is a difference between half-half
and all-all. So again, a little bit confusing, but according to רבא
Rava he says that the רבנן rabbanan would agree if you sold
half and freed half that the slave would be free. Here's a
case of giving your property to two slaves. Sounds like it's the
same scenario; they should each like be half-free of one another. But
the ברייתא braita says it doesn't work. Well, one ברייתא braita says
it does and one says it doesn't. What's the reason for not
to work according to רבא? Rava? Either it's one שטר, shtar, therefore
there's a technical problem that you can't have a שטר שחרור shtar
shichrur for two slaves, or the way we're now reading into the
ברייתא, braita, even if you gave two שטרות, shtaros, there would be
a difference of all-all and half-half. And the way תוספות Tosafos explains,
from half-half when you're dealing with two slaves, since it doesn't work
in sequence, it won't work simultaneously either. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ואי בעית אימא, v'ee ba'is eima, if you want to say, לא
קשיא כאן בבת אחת כאן בזה אחר זה, lo kashya kan b'vas
achas kan b'zeh achar zeh, which is exactly what we've been getting
to, that when does it work
when you give it all away to two slaves? If it's all
at the same time. If it's sequential, then obviously it does not
work because then according to the רבנן rabbanan you cannot half-free a
slave. Okay. בשלמא בתרא לא קני דקא קני ליה קמא. bishlama basra
lo kani d'ka kani lei kama. Now the גמרא Gemara says, one
minute,
in the case of זה אחר זה, zeh achar zeh, if it
was actually a case that you said כולו, kulo, not חציו, chetzyo,
so we understand why the second guy doesn't get anything because the
first guy got it all. אלא קמא ליקני לנפשיה וליקני לחבריה, ela
kama likni l'nafshei v'likni l'chavreih, but
if you say to one slave, I'm giving you all, and then
afterwards the next slave, I'm giving you all, why do we say
it doesn't work? I understand why it doesn't work for the second
slave. Why doesn't it work for the first slave? He got it
all. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מחוורתא כדשינין מעיקרא, ela mechavarta
k'deshinin mei'ikara, so fine, we'll go back to our earlier answers. Okay.
So bottom line is רבא Rava says the רבנן rabbanan would agree
when you sold and gave half your slave away, that would just
be like already it's half-owned and you freed half, and that is
one ברייתא braita when you give to two slaves they each own
each other half way. And the ברייתא braita that it doesn't work
is either it's in one שטר shtar or it was two שטרות
shtaros at חצי חצי. chetzi chetzi. And that's חצי חצי chetzi chetzi
to two slaves doesn't work even though חצי חצי chetzi chetzi to
a slave and a free person does work. Okay.
That's that. Now moving on to the next topic.
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, שאני התם דקא קרי להו עבדאי.
shani hasam d'ka kari lehu avadai.
No, no, no. The only reason it didn't work in that second
ברייתא, braita, really of course it should have worked. I don't know,
two שטרות, shtaros, חצי חצי, chetzi chetzi, whatever it would be. It
works fine, like רבא Rava said, it works according to the רבנן.
rabbanan. But the only problem was you said, all of my property
is given to my, these two slaves of mine. Okay.
Frederick and Enrique, my two slaves. So, I don't know why I'm
having French slaves. Anyway, so those two slaves. You called them your
two slaves, which means that you clearly what you in your mind
thought they would remain slaves and own property. But because you referred
to them as slaves, it meant that you weren't freeing them. So
that's the only reason it doesn't work. Of course it could work
if you were clearly freeing them at the same time and even
if you were giving half of them to one another, you were
doing it as a type of a חצי חצי. chetzi chetzi. So
the גמרא Gemara says that's why, because you said עבדאי. avadai. So
אמר ליה רפרם לרב אשי, amar lei Rafram l'Rav Ashi, so רפרם
Rafram said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ודילמא עבדאי שהיו כבר, v'dilma
avadai shehayu kvar,
maybe he means that they've been my slaves until now. How do
you say, why do you assume it means that you're continuing to
retain them as your slaves? So מי לא תנן, mi lo tnan,
did we not learn in a משנה? mishna? הכותב כל נכסיו לעבדו,
hakoseiv kol nechasav l'avdo, you wrote over all your property to your
slave, יצא לחירות, yatza l'cheirus, so that also serves as a writ
of freedom since you're giving him to himself and he goes free.
Now שייר קרקע כל שהוא, shiyer karka kol shehu, if you left
over a little bit of land, okay, so you said I'm giving
all my property to you except this little garden patch I have
in the front yard, לא יצא לחירות, lo yatza l'cheirus,
he does not go free. Why? Because that's the position of לא
פלגינן דיבורא. lo palginan dibura. That since you are not, since in
that statement you are not fully giving over what you say, you
say everything except, there's a sense of holding back. That sense of
holding back, the same way there's a holding back on the property
that you're giving him, we interpret it as a type of a
holding back on his freedom as well. And therefore he does not
go free.
Even though clearly you're only saying this little garden patch, you're not
freeing him, but nevertheless since there is that holding back in the
שטר, shtar, that applies to the slave as well.
Now רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, לעולם הוא בן חורין עד
שיאמר כל נכסיי נתונים לפלוני עבדי חוץ מאחד מריבוא שבהן. l'olam hu
ben chorin ad sheyomar kol nechasai nesunim lifloni avdi chutz mi'echad m'ribo
shebahen. No, in that case... anything you even say everything
except the following plots of land that doesn't affect his freedom. But
if you said I'm giving you everything except one one-millionth of my
property and you don't designate what that millionth is, then he isn't
free. Because maybe that one one-millionth is partly him or is all
of him and therefore that's why it does not work because it's
not a full writ of freedom. Okay, so now all of that
is interesting, by the way that seems more consistent with the רבנן
Rabbanan that you can't half free a slave, because if you could
half free your slave with a writ, then why should that not
work even if you're not fully freeing him? But anyway what's important
for us is that it says הכותב כל נכסיו לעבדו hakoteiv kol
nechasav le'avdo to your slave. So the גמרא Gemara says טעמא דאמר
חוץ מאחד מריבוא שבהם. tama de'amar chutz mi'echad meribu shebahem. Does it
mean that it doesn't work because you held part back and you
said except for one-one millionth? הא לא אמר הכי קני. ha lo
amar hachi kani. It would work even though רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
says עד שיאמר כל נכסיי נתונים לפלוני עבדי. ad sheyomar kol nechasai
netunim liploni avdi. So even though you're saying פלוני עבדי, ploni avdi,
so-and-so my slave, it still works. So אמאי והא עבדי קא קרי
ליה? amai veha avdi ka kari lei? You're calling him a slave.
אלא עבדי שהיה כבר. ela avdi shehaya kvar. You mean that he's
been my slave until now. הכא נמי עבדי שהיה כבר. hacha nami
avdi shehaya kvar. Here he'll also be slave until now. So saying
that the whole reason it didn't work before when you tried to
give it all to two slaves is because you called them slave,
that doesn't prove anything. That means that they've been my slaves until
this point. But basically if you try to give over all of
your property, is it going to work or not, that
might be based on רבנן Rabbanan versus רבי, Rebbi, whether you can
half free a slave. רבא's Rava point is that even the רבנן
Rabbanan would agree that you could half free there because you're completely
divesting yourself of your slaves. And then it might have something to
do with did you say כל kol all to both slaves or
did you say half-half? Would half-half work because that wouldn't work sequentially
or maybe they'd not work because you wrote both of them in
the same שטר? Shtar? And like a גט Get you can't have
two written in one שטר. Shtar. Okay, now we go
on. It's a little complicated. That was the end of the discussion
of רבי Rebbi and the רבנן. Rabbanan. Now we go on to
a different issue, which is more I think conceptual about the question
of the status of this half-free
slave. Alright, so let's take a look.
Now you have this slave that is half-free and this would be
let's say before בית הלל Beis Hillel decided to rule or reversed
themselves and ruled like בית שמאי Beis Shammai and decided that he's
going to remain half himself, half of the time work for himself,
half of the time work for his master. And that's going to
be a stable situation. So how is that going to play out
in things that don't just have to do with מצוה? Mitzvah? So
let's take a look. נגחו שור יום של רבו לרבו. negacho shor
yom shel rabo lerabo. Let's say he was gored by an ox
on the day that he had designated to work for his master.
Okay, he's off on שבת, Shabbos, so Sunday, Tuesday, and Thursday he
works for his master, Monday, Wednesday, and Friday he works for himself.
So if this happens on one of his master's days,
so that day he was considered his master's slave, so the master
collect the damages for the goring. Okay, so נגחו שור יום של
רבו לרבו, negacho shor yom shel rabo lerabo, יום של עצמו לעצמו.
yom shel atzmo le'atzmo. His day, if he was gored by himself
he gets the damage payment. Now of course the funny thing about
this is is that the effect of those damages are going to
last much more beyond that one day. So you would think that
on that day you can say the labor belongs to the master,
but in terms of what's his identity, who owns him, on any
given day he's half owned by himself, half owned by his master.
And you should say so who collects for the damages? You should
say you should split it. That would be the logical thing to
say. Okay, so this is very strange that on the day he's
working for his master he's considered to be in all monetary matters,
although in personal status matters he remains half-half, in all monetary matters
on that day he's considered to be fully his master's. So the
גמרא Gemara says Tali you're on camera right now for anybody who's
watching. So he's the גמרא Gemara says יום של רבו לרבו,
יום של עצמו לעצמו. yom shel rabo lerabo, yom shel atzmo le'atzmo.
The גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if that's true יום
של רבו ישא שפחה יום של עצמו ישא בת חורין? yom shel
rabo yisa shifcha yom shel atzmo yisa bas chorin? So first the
גמרא Gemara takes it to the absurd. If his really his identity
switches on each day, well then why doesn't he be married to
a free woman on the day that he's his own and he's
a free person,
and be married to a slave woman on the day he's his
master, then he's a hundred percent a slave? So it says no.
איסורא לא קאמרינן. issura lo kaamrinan. We're not talking about his status,
איסורין. issurin. In the status he's half-half. But we're talking about the
question about ownership, who owns him. Now even there you would say
he's
owned half-half. The labor alternates days, but the גמרא Gemara seems to
be saying that no, he's always personal status half-half, but in terms
of ownership on the day that he's working for himself he's fully
owned by himself, on the day that he's working for his master
he is fully owned by his master. So the גמרא Gemara says
תא שמע ta shema come here, חצי עבד וחצי בן חורין chatzi
eved vechatzi ben chorin נותנים חצי קנס לרבו וחצי כופר ליורשיו. notnim
chatzi knas lerabo vechatzi kofer leyorshav. So here you have
a case not of damage and injury. that he was gored and
he that he was gored and and he was killed in the
process. And there the הלכה halacha is that what happens if it's
a slave, you pay a קנס, knas, pay a fine to the
master. If it's a free person, you pay a כופר, kofer, you
pay a redemption fee, not a redemption fee, excuse me, you know,
a type of an atonement fee, and that goes to the heirs
if an ox gores a free person. So here it says that
what happens if he's gored? So it says, it doesn't say it
depends on what who he's working for on that day. If he's
gored and he dies, then you say he was half-owned by himself,
half-owned by his master. So half the fine goes to himself and
half of the כופר, kofer, excuse me, half the...
so the part that's half-owned by the master, half the fine goes
to the master, and the part that's half-owned by himself where he's
considered to be a free person, that's not a fine, that's not
a קנס, knas, that's a כופר, kofer, and the כופר kofer there,
that atonement payment, that goes to his heirs. Now the גמרא Gemara
is going to ask what type of an heirs does he have,
we'll worry about that in a minute. Basically, what you see here
is when the ox gores him and he dies in the process,
it doesn't matter whose day of work it was. That's a monetary
issue, and even for a monetary issue we say he's half-half. Okay,
so how is that different than being gored and injured? So the
גמרא Gemara says אמאי, amai, why is that true?
הכא נמי נימא ליה, hacha nami nima leh, let's here also say
יום שרבו לרבו יום שלעצמו לעצמו, yom sherabo lerabo yom shele'atzmo le'atzmo,
that in terms of the question of who owns him as a
monetary issue it should depend whose day he's working, which day it
is and who he's working for. גמרא Gemara says no, שאני הכא
דקא כליה קרנא. shani hacha deka kalya karna. Here it's different because
the principal has been destroyed, which basically means that now that he's
been killed, it's not a question of just like which day. Like
there it really is a full question of what was his full
identity as who, you know, who owned him. That's a permanent type
of a question because he's dead now, there's no ongoing question about
it. So who owned him?
He was half-owned by each and therefore you define it that way.
But if it's something that is a question that's not permanent, so
in terms of non-permanent monetary matters, not a question of bottom line
who fully owns him, but like who is he working for, you
know, that type of a thing is assessed on a day-to-day basis.
And I have to say I still really don't fully understand, right?
Because even if today he's working for the master and he gets
gored, it doesn't mean that on today he's, you know, he's fully
owned by the master. This question of who owns him is still
half-and-half. So why the damages go, it seems like what the way
the גמרא Gemara is looking at it is that if he was
gored on the day that he was owned by his master, then
that's considered almost the proceeds of the work that he is doing
that day. One of the things that he gained out of him
today, one of the things that he produced today was the payment
of damages. And if it was his day, that goes to him,
that was his work for the day. If it was his master's
day, that goes to his master. So we don't assess it by
saying the payment goes to the person who owns him and he's
half-owned, and ownership doesn't switch day-by-day. Presumably we say it as this
payment goes to,
this is a sort of an earnings that came from him and
it goes to the person that's entitled to today's earnings. Whereas if
he's completely killed, then it's not a question of earnings. Then it's
a question of this piece of property or whatever, where this person
was killed, this property was destroyed, what was his basic status? And
the status was half-owned and half-free. Okay, so that seems to be
the difference of כליה קרנא kalya karna and not כליה קרנא. kalya
karna. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
So the גמרא Gemara says ואלא היכי דמי דלא כליה קרנא, ve'ela
heichi dami delo kalya karna, what would be a case that he
would be gored that it would not be permanent damage? Okay, because
now the גמרא Gemara is understanding even more that if it's permanent
damage it does not have to mean that he was actually killed.
If it was literally a permanent damage, his arm was torn off,
so that's we can't look at that as that was today's earnings,
the money you got from the arm. That's a fundamental question that
the property was damaged in a permanent way, and then it goes
to the owner, and if he the owner his master and the
owner they're both the owners and they split it. So if he's
being killed, it goes by the fundamental question that he's half-owned by
both and it's split. And when he's permanently injured and his arm
is torn off, it goes by the fundamental question of who owns
him and they both own him and it's split. So which question
is seen as one of earnings and not one of fundamental who
owns him, and something that would be defined based on the day
it would be? ואלא היכי דמי דלא כליה קרנא? ve'ela heichi dami
delo kalya karna? So the גמרא Gemara says כגון שהכהו על ידו
וטימטמה ידו. kagon shehikahu al yado vetimtima yado.
Let's say the ox hit him on his arm and his arm
like swelled up, וסופה לחזור, vesofa lachazor, in the end it will
heal. So it's infected and whatever, it's going to take months until
it heals, but eventually it will heal. So the property has not
really been damaged in a permanent way. So it's not a question
of, well, you broke this object, who do you pay? You pay
the owners, they're half-owned. The object isn't broken, it's just currently unusable.
So he loses out, he can't work, so labor is lost, but
the object has not been destroyed. So then it's a question of
seen as oh, as a result of this injury, you get a
payment, but the object, meaning the person, has not been destroyed for
damage, you know, broken, that it would go to the owners, it's
just a temporary situation. Ultimately, the owners are going to fully own
their property. He's going to be better, he's going to be fully
owned by the owners, he's going to be fully owned by the
owner. So the owners haven't lost even part of the property, they've
just lost his earnings. And therefore, on that day, any money that
came as a result of that goes to the person who is
entitled to his earnings that day, whether it's the slave or whether
it's the master. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says סופו לחזור, sofo
lachzor, so that's the case.
So the גמרא Gemara says
הניחא לאביי, hani nicha le'Abaye,
that's good according to אביי, Abaye, דאמר נותן לו שבת גדולה ושבת
קטנה, de'amar noten lo shevet gedola ve'shevet ketana, שפיר. shapir. אלא לרבא
דאמר אין נותן לו אלא שבתו שבכל יום ויום,
ela le'Rava de'amar ein noten
lo ela shivto shebechol yom va'yom, השתא הוא דשורו ושר אינו משלם
אלא נזק. hashta hu deshoro vesher eino meshalem ela nezek.
So here the גמרא Gemara has an interesting question. How do we
conceptualize a case when a person is hurt and damaged in this
way that he's going to get better, but right now it's infected,
it's swollen, it's going to take a long time? If this were
a question about somebody
that damaged another person,
how would we conceptualize it? Now, when a person damages another person
חבלה, chavala, personal injury, there are five types of payment.
There's צער, tza'ar, pain and suffering, נזק, nezek, the actual cost, the
actual damage itself, ריפוי, ripui, doctors' bills still, שבת, shevet, the time
that he's out of work because of the injury, and בושת, boshet,
the embarrassment. The part that's important to us is the נזק nezek
and the שבת. shevet. Now in a case of permanent injury, the
leg was torn off. So how much is the damage? Well, you
use it based on the slave market because how else do you
assign a dollar value to a human being? And you say how
much would he have been worth as a slave with the leg
and without the leg? And that's the cost of the leg. Now
what's שבת, shevet, the time he's out of work? It's not the
amount of work that he's lost, the job he can't do because
he doesn't have the leg. That's all already considered to be incorporated
into the value of the leg itself when you determine the value
of the leg. So what's the שבת, shevet, the time he's out
of work? Is that even while he's recuperating in the hospital from
the injury, if he weren't recuperating, if he was out of the
hospital, he was without his leg, there's work that he could do.
And the work that he's not able to do because he's recuperating,
that's the שבת. shevet. So נזק nezek is the actual cost of
the injury in terms of what he's going to be like after
he gets out of the hospital and so on, and the שבת
shevet is the time he's in the hospital that he can't be
working even in his current condition.
Now what would be the story if it was not a permanent
damage? It was this case, the arm was like totally swollen up
and he's going to be in the hospital and there's going to
be like, you know, for three months. Okay, and even in the
three months, right, that he's going to, so how do you figure
out the payment? So one easy way, which is what רבא Rava
says, is, well, there's no נזק, nezek, there's no permanent damage, it's
all just time he's in the hospital. And when he fully recovers,
then he'll be, you know, then he'll be able
to go back to his normal job. So you just pay him,
every day you pay him the, you know, the total, the cost
that he's out of work. And if it divides itself up into
two stages, right, the first part he can't do any work because
he's just in so much pain and recovery and whatever, right? And
then the second part, because the arm is still swollen,
he can't do his normal job, but he can do some type
of job. He can go and be, the גמרא Gemara says, watch
cucumbers, but while, but for the first weeks he couldn't do anything,
then you divide the payment. For the first week, he's completely out
of work, and his normal job was, I don't know, whatever it
was, a doctor, computer programmer, you pay him his full-time
salary. The second week, he's able to watch cucumbers because he's not
in pain and suffering, but he still can't go back to his
job of being a doctor. So then you pay him the difference
between being a doctor and watching cucumbers. But anyway, the entire time
there's no נזק nezek payment, it's all
just you figure out what he's not, what job he's not able
to do because of his current situation, and that's what you pay
him for. That's what רבא Rava says. אביי Abaye says no, you
actually pay him what's called שבת גדולה ושבת קטנה. shevet gedola ve'shevet
ketana. שבת גדולה Shevet gedola is the fact of and you consider
it as נזק nezek that he cannot currently,
you know, do his major job. So the fact that you go
ahead and you look at the slave market, and you don't say
like how much labor is he losing because he can't do his
major job, that's how you look at שבת. shevet. You say no,
how much would a slave be worth currently with this injury even
though it's an injury that's only going to last three months. and
compare that to a slave without that injury. So that's the נזק.
nezek. And then the שבת, shevet, that's already now that you've incorporated
the injury, now there's a time that he's going to be, he
can't even do the cucumber watching job because he's going to be
in bed.
So, according to אביי, Abaye, the גמרא Gemara says, we get it.
According to אביי, Abaye, there's a value here of נזק. nezek. How
much is he worth without this injury on the slave market and
with this injury? And that's what the שור shor will pay. But
according to רבא, Rava, says the גמרא, Gemara, it's only שבת. shevet.
It's only time out of work. Now this idea of time out
of work, this is something that is only paid for personal injury.
When an ox gores a human being, the ox doesn't pay embarrassment,
and it doesn't pay suffering, and it doesn't pay doctors' bills, and
it doesn't pay for the time the person is out of work.
Well, the ox doesn't pay anything, but the owner does pay. But
the only thing that the owner pays for is the actual change
in value on the slave market. So, back to where we were.
We were saying this עבד, eved, if it's a permanent injury, then
it goes by who owns him, and it's divided by himself and
the master between himself and the master. The only time when it
would be seen as an earnings issue and based on whose day
it was, was that it was not a permanent injury, but that
it was a temporary injury that he was going to fully recover
from. So the גמרא Gemara says, well, listen. According to אביי, Abaye,
even a temporary injury is something an ox you would pay for
in case of a goring ox. Because we would still look at
it on the slave market and the change of value and we
would define it as נזק nezek and a goring and in a
case of goring ox it would be paid for. So it's a
type of a נזק nezek which really isn't a permanent damage and
that would go by the person's day to the person whose day
it was. But according to רבא, Rava, there would be no payment
for this if an ox temporarily put him out of work. Because
that's just a question of
there's no damage, permanent damage, there's no damages to be assessed, it's
only payment for time out of work. And that is only paid
in a case of personal injury, not a case when an ox
injures. So what is that scenario? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, וצריכתא. u'tzrichta.
So אלא ella גמרא Gemara says,
הניחא לאביי דמנסי ליה שבת גדולה ושבת קטנה. haniha le'Abaye de'mansei lei
shevet gedola u'shevet ketana. So that whole longer explanation was in these
two words of the גמרא. Gemara. That works for אביי Abaye that
says in a case of one person injuring another in this scenario
of a non-permanent injury, there's שבת גדולה, shevet gedola, which means we
actually base it on the slave market, even though it's only a
temporary injury, and שבת קטנה, shevet ketana, the time that right now
he's in the hospital that he's out of any work. שפיר, shappir,
so there's an idea of actual damages to be assessed. אלא לרבא
דאמר אינו נותן לו אלא ששה סלעים בכל יום ויום. ella le'Rava
de'amar eino noten lo ella shisha sela'im be'chol yom va'yom.
But according to רבא Rava that says that in the case of
personal injury, you don't do the slave market, you only base it
on the time out of work if it's not a permanent injury.
האי שור הוא. hai shor hu. This is the case of an
ox that gores. ושור אינו משלם אלא נזק. ve'shor eino meshalem ella
nezek. שור shor only pays for the actual cost of injury. And
רבא Rava is saying that there's no injury here. We don't assess
it as damage, we only assess it as time out of work.
So according to רבא, Rava, what is the scenario of a non-permanent
damage
that would get paid by an ox in the case of an
ox? So the גמרא Gemara says, איבעית אימא כשהיכהו אדם. ee'ba'it eima
keshe'hikahu adam. Fine.
So although it sounded like before we were saying that he was
gored when the slave gets paid right when you know when it
depends on whose day it was. Now you force me to say
it's not a case of goring. If it's a case of goring,
it's equally divided by both parties. That's a case of real injury
and that goes to the owners. When does it go to the
person whose day it was? When it was done by a person.
And it was a non-permanent injury and it was a payment only
of loss of labor and that would go to the person whose
day it was because that's seen as a type of a proceeds
and not as a question of the slave being damaged. ואיבעית אימא,
ve'ee'ba'it eima, and if you want I could say, מימרא הוא. memra
hu. מימרא דרבא לא סבירא ליה. memra de'Rava lo sevira lei. It's
just a teaching, it's not a ברייתא, braita, it's not a משנה,
mishna, and therefore רבא Rava doesn't have to agree with it. But
you're right, it's not consistent with רבא. Rava. Okay. So what have
we said? Meaning that was a little complicated but very conceptually important.
We said that this slave, no matter what day it is, he's
half slave half free person in terms of personal status. And no
matter what day it is, he's half owned by himself and half
owned by his master. So anything that had to do with his
fundamental question of who owned him, like if there was a he
was killed or it was a permanent injury, it would be divided
equally between him and his master. The only thing that we would
say is that if there would be a type of unusual earnings
that would have resulted on that day but was not seen as
a question of ownership of who owned him, then it would go
to the person whose day it was. And that scenario would work
according to אביי Abaye if an ox or a human did not
cause a permanent injury. And in that case there's a payment of
damages, but
which would be paid in the case of an ox, but because
the slave is not permanently damaged that payment doesn't go to the
owners and divided equally, that payment goes to the person who's entitled
to the slave's earnings on this particular day. And that's why it
would depend on whose day it was.
Okay, that was a little complicated. Let's take a look now at
the next piece. איבעיא להו, ibay'u lo, they asked the following question.
מחוסר גט שחרור, m'chusar get shichror, יש לו קנס yesh lo knas
או אין לו קנס? o ein lo knas? Now we're dealing not
with the half-half aspect, but with another way of half-half, this fascinating
case of the slave that is not owned at all as property,
but he is
actually—he is not yet free. He has to get a גט שחרור.
get shichror. A case would be for example, you know, the גמרא
Gemara before if somebody is מפקיר mafkir his slave that he has
to—he is a slave that is not owned at all as property
but he is still awaiting his גט שחרור get shichror and he
still has to be freed. Another example would be our case, where
he taught like בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, and now you force the
master to free him, so there he is—that's a little more complicated
because it has both aspects: he's half owned and half free, and
he's also awaiting a גט שחרור. get shichror. Okay, so even but
the easier case, the non-complicated case, is that he's fully not owned,
but he is still awaiting his גט שחרור get shichror to change
his personal status. And now as we said, if you remember from
earlier discussions, that was a very fascinating idea that the master's still
considered enough of the status of master to write a גט שחרור
get shichror even though there's no property ownership left altogether. And that
was somewhat debated in the גמרא: Gemara: can the master still do
it, does the master need to do it and so on. So
here we are assuming this very interesting middle ground, that he is
completely not owned as property, his personal status has not changed, the
master's still enough of a master to write a גט שחרור, get
shichror, and he has to write it but he hasn't written it.
So then for which הלכות halachos would he might still be considered
to be belonging to his master, even though as a property way
he completely belongs to himself? So let's take a look. איבעיא להו,
ibay'u lo, they raised the question: מחוסר גט שחרור, m'chusar get shichror,
יש לו קנס yesh lo knas או אין לו קנס? o ein
lo knas? Do you pay the thirty שקל shekel or not? כסף
שלשים שקלים יתן לאדוניו, kesef shloshim shekalim yiten leadonav, אמר רחמנא: amar
Rachmana: give the thirty שקל shekel to the master, והאי לאו אדוניה,
vehai lav adoneih, and this guy's no longer the master, he doesn't
really own him anymore. Okay, or maybe
you pay nothing, not כופר kofer because he's not yet a free
man, not קנס knas because there's no אדון. adon. We don't know
what the alternative would be. But anyway, would you give the קנס
knas to the master? So would you say he's not really a
master? או דלמא, o dilma, or you say, כיון דמחוסר גט שחרור,
keivan dem'chusar get shichror, אדון קרינן ביה, adon karinan beih, since he's
awaiting this change of status and this גט שחרור, get shichror, and
in order for the other person to give him the גט שחרור
get shichror he has to have a status as a master, so
therefore maybe he is considered enough of a master to collect the
קנס. knas. Okay, so because he is still a slave in terms
of his personal status, maybe and that may define the guy as
the master. Now you could say that if he doesn't own him
as property, why is he entitled to קנס? knas? But the answer
here is well, how do you conceive of also why you pay
the thirty שקל shekel when the ox gores a slave? Since it's
not a payment of the actual value, it's a קנס, knas, it's
a fine, it's arbitrary, it's always thirty שקל, shekel, maybe it doesn't
require that you actually own the slave as property. Maybe as long
as you're the master. My ox gored a slave, that was irresponsible
of me, like when it gores a free person I also don't
pay value, I pay כופר, kofer, I was to blame, maybe I'm
the one being punished, it's not so much a payment of loss
of property. So maybe even if the other person doesn't own him
as property, just is designated as the master, that would be enough
for me to pay the שלשים שקל. shloshim shekel. So the גמרא
Gemara doesn't know. Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, let's see, it's going
to try to prove. תא שמע: ta shma: הממית מי שחציו עבד
וחציו בן חורין, hamamit mi shechatzi eved vechatzi ben chorin, this is
what we just said, a case of half and half, it gored
a guy who's half slave, half free, so נושא חצי קנס לרבו
וחצי כופר ליורשיו, nosei chatzi knas lerabo vechatzi kofer liyorshav,
you pay half of the קנס knas to the master and half
of the כופר kofer to the heirs. So now what is—now why
did that prove anything? The master there is not—fully owns him as
property. He's not in the process of giving him a גט שחרור,
get shichror, he actually fully owns him halfway. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, מאי לאו במשחרנא? mai lav bimshachrana?
Maybe we're talking like the second part of the משנה, mishnah, where
now בית הלל Beis Hillel agreed to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, and
בית הלל Beis Hillel says you're right, you have to free him
and you have to write a גט שחרור. get shichror. So according
to that, he should be seen of as somebody that now because
חז"ל Chazal are demanding that he be freed, that maybe fundamentally he's
already not owned by his master, he's only awaiting a גט שחרור,
get shichror, so maybe that should be like an analogous case and
nevertheless you pay half the קנס knas to the master. So
the גמרא Gemara says, מאי לאו במשחרנא? mai lav bimshachrana? לא, במשנה
ראשונה. lo, b'mishnah rishonah. No, that doesn't prove anything, that could be
before בית הלל Beis Hillel agreed to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, and
you fully own him half slave, you're not going to give him
a גט שחרור, get shichror, it's a stable situation, and you can't
prove anything from that to our case where the guy is fully
unowned—not owned by the guy by the master and only awaiting a
גט שחרור. get shichror. Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, let's try to
prove it again. הפיל את שינו וסימא את עינו. hipil et shino
vesime et eino.
The master knocked out the slave's tooth and blinded his eye, which
we know those are things that any one of them he goes
free. So the הלכה halacha is יוצא בשינו, yotzei b'shino, he gets
free by
his
tooth and
So this would be exactly our case, מעוכב שטר שחרור, me'ukav shtar
shichrur, basically the master no longer has any אריסות. arisut. I'm assuming
that once there's a demand to write a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur,
there's no longer any monetary claim over him. The master hasn't freed
him yet in this case, or didn't pronounce ownership, but nevertheless, we're
assuming once the שטר shtar says that he goes free, that means
that the master no longer has any monetary right to the slave,
but he has to write a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. So we
think it's exactly our case. And what do you see? That even
in that case, the master now blinds the slave's eye and is
going to pay the slave for the eye. Okay, so even though
he still is the master and demand, and has to write a
שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. אי אמרת יש לו קנס, ei amart yesh
lo knas,
if the master would get a קנס knas if the slave was
gored,
וקנסא לרבו, veknasa l'rabo, התם חבל ביה אחריני יהבי לרבו, hatam chaval
beih achrinei yahavi l'rabo,
if other people injure him, it goes to the master. So יהבי
לרבו. yahavi l'rabo. חבל ביה רבו גופיה יהבי לדידיה, chaval beih rabbo
gufayah yahvei l'didei,
if the master injures him, would it go to the slave? Meaning
if the הלכה halacha is that while he's in a case of
מעוכב גט שחרור, me'ukav get shichrur, the master's still entitled to the
payment of קנס, knas, then the master should be able to keep
the payment of personal
injury. Now I don't personally understand that because the issue about personal
injury that really is a question of who owns him monetarily, and
the slave owns himself monetarily, and of course it kind of go
to the slave. The only reason I thought קנס knas made sense
was because קנס knas maybe wasn't a payment of loss of property,
and therefore קנס knas wasn't the payment of loss of property, it
could maybe be not, that should go to the person who still
has to give him a גט שחרור, get shichrur, even though he
doesn't own him monetarily. But in this case, once you don't own
him monetarily, why should you be entitled? The גמרא Gemara somehow seeing
it all in the same פרשה, parsha, that maybe even though there's
no monetary ownership and I can't work the slave and I'm not
entitled to his earnings, but since I'm still his master, any payment
that comes as a result of something that happened to him, maybe
that should go to me, whether that's קנס knas or whether that's
חבלה. chavala. And this proves that that's not the case by חבלה,
chavala, that if I'm חובל chovel in him, it goes to him
and doesn't stay with me. So the גמרא Gemara says doesn't that
prove our case? So the גמרא Gemara says no. אימא כיון דאמר
אינו
צריך,
eima keivan d'amar
eino tzarich, maybe
this is going with the opinion that says that when I knock
out my slave's tooth, he doesn't need a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur.
So it's not even our scenario, he automatically went free. And then
when his eye was blinded, he was already a completely free person
and that was the end of the
story. Okay, where are we? דתניא דתנו רבנן, d'tanya d'tanu rabanan, בכולן
עבד יוצא לחירות, b'kulan eved yotzei l'cherut, וצריך גט שחרור, v'tzarich get
shichrur, מרבו. merabo.
In all of these cases about
about about breaking or whatever destroying eye or tooth or any of
like a fingers or any of the sort of appendages, you know
he ever goes free and needs to get שחרור. shichrur. דברי רבי
ישמעאל. divrei Rabbi Yishmael. That's what Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי מאיר אומר
אינו צריך. Rabbi Meir omer eino tzarich.
He does not need a גט get שטר, shtar, he automatically goes
free without any שטר. shtar. רבי אליעזר אומר צריך, Rabbi Eliezer omer
tzarich, רבי טרפון אומר אינו צריך, Rabbi Tarfon omer eino tzarich, רבי
עקיבא אומר צריך. Rabbi Akiva omer tzarich. So it's
back and forth does he need or not need. המכריעין לפני חכמים,
hamachri'in lifnei chachamim, those who decide, you know, in front of the
sages, whatever that means, רש"י Rashi says he doesn't know what that's
referring to, המכריעין, hamachri'in, basically they try to weigh the different opinions
here because we have all these תנאים, tannaim, some say he does
need a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, some say he doesn't. So they
came out with a compromise. נראים דברי רבי טרפון בשן ועין, nir'im
divrei Rabbi Tarfon beshein va'ayin, Rabbi Tarfon who says he doesn't need
a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, that's by an eye, a tooth and
an eye. הואיל ותורה כתבה לו. ho'il v'torah katvah lo. Since that's
from the תורה Torah and therefore he goes free without a שטר
שחרור. shtar shichrur. ודברי רבי עקיבא בשאר איברים. v'divrei Rabbi Akiva bish'ar
eivarim. But Rabbi Akiva by the other limbs. הואיל וקנס חכמים הוא.
ho'il u'knas chachamim hu. Since that's only a fine imposed by the
sages. Now the גמרא Gemara gets very upset because although the תורה
Torah only mentioned eye and tooth, we understand by that as that
that's meant to include other appendages. So the גמרא, Gemara, and why
are we calling only a rabbinic fine? We understand that that's biblical.
So the גמרא Gemara says קנסא קרא כתיב ביה, knasa kra ktiv
beih, we learned that out from פסוקים. psukim. אלא אימא הואיל ומדרש
חכמים הוא. ela eima ho'il u'midrash chachamim hu.
Since it's only learned from a מדרש, midrash, he'll need a שטר
שחרור. shtar shichrur. Now what's the logic? Who cares if it's learned
from a מדרש midrash or not? If the תורה Torah says he
goes free without a שטר, shtar, he goes free without a שטר.
shtar. So there's a very nice little תוספות. Tosafot. He says הואיל
ומדרש חכמים הוא, ho'il u'midrash chachamim hu, this brings in an idea
from an earlier גמרא, Gemara, so it says אמר רבינו תם, amar
Rabbeinu Tam, דחיישינן שמא ימצאנו בשוק, d'chaishinan shema yimtza'enu bashuk, ויאמר לו
עבדי אתה, v'yomar lo avdi atah, that
if he doesn't have a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, a guy will,
okay, he broke off his pinky, but he'll say, yeah, you're still
my slave, you don't go free with that. אבל בשן ועין לא
חיישינן, aval beshein va'ayin lo chaishinan, because it's so so evident, but
by שן ועין beshein va'ayin he'll never be able to claim that,
everybody will say what do you mean he's missing missing an eye,
he's missing a tooth, just look at the פסוקים psukim in the
תורה. Torah. as explicit in the Torah, we might want to give
the slave more evidence and demand that the slave get a שטר
שחרור. shtar shichrur. So anyway, back to our point, what is the
status of this slave that is awaiting a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur,
is he free after his tooth has been knocked out? So the
גמרא Gemara says, well maybe he's not awaiting a שטר שחרור shtar
shichrur if his tooth has been knocked out. There are all these
positions and the compromise position as well, which is that he goes
free automatically and doesn't even need a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. So
of course if he's injured afterwards, the slave collects, he's automatically a
free person. What would be the status of somebody who is not
owned monetarily by the master, but is still awaiting לקבל l'kabel a
גט שחרור? get shichrur? To what degree is the master still considered
the master? Would he collect קנס? knas? Would he collect חבלה? chabala?
The גמרא Gemara does not yet know the answer to that. Again,
as far as I, as far as, you know, it would seem
to me that the issue of would he collect חבלה chabala would
be much more obvious that the master would not. That's a monetary
issue and the slave owns himself. Would he collect קנס? knas? That
may be דצריך עיון, d'tzarich iyun, maybe more has to do with
the person's formal status as master, not an actual question of property
ownership. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara does not yet resolve that question,
and we're going to go on tomorrow with the question not about
things that are monetary, which would seem to have maybe more of
a more obvious answer that the slave should collect it once he's
not owned from a monetary perspective, but we're going to get onto
things which are more somewhat an issue of personal status, so we'll
be continuing with this tomorrow.